Guide to the Theodore and Ruth Lidz Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Theodore and Ruth Lidz papers
1927-2001
MS 895
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
20
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and data files documenting the professional careers of Ruth and Theodore Lidz. The papers focus on their professional lives, particularly from the 1950s to the 1980s, highlighting the Lidzes' study of the importance of the family environment in cases of schizophrenia.
Lidz, Theodore
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Theodore Lidz, 1978 and 1995-1996; and of the estate of Theodore Lidz, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
Letters of recommendation in box 14 are closed for seventy-five years from the date of creation as established by Yale Corporation regulations.
Research data in boxes 28-45 is closed for seventy-five years from the date of creation (2011-2060). Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
Biographical / Historical
Theodore and Ruth Lidz were psychoanalysts who collaborated on the study and treatment of schizophrenia and also were interested in the art and anthropology of the indigenous people of the South Pacific. During a long career, Theodore Lidz wrote more than 175 articles and eight books exploring familial, social, and cultural factors involved in normal development and the development of mental disorders. Ruth Lidz also studied the psychological aspects of abortion, human fertility, and the problems of pregnant adolescents.
Theodore Lidz was born on April 1, 1910, in New York City. He attended Columbia College and the Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons, receiving his B.A. in 1931 and his M.D. in 1936. After two years of medical internship at New Haven Hospital, he moved to Baltimore. In 1938, he became a resident in psychiatry at the Henry Phipps Psychiatric Clinic, Johns Hopkins University.
Ruth Wilmanns Lidz was born on June 18, 1910, in Heidelberg, Germany, the daughter of Karl Wilmanns, a professor of psychiatry at Heidelberg University and the granddaughter of the chemist Victor Meyer. Leaving Germany in the middle of her medical studies because she could no longer live under the Hitler regime, she spent a year in Sweden and completed her medical degree at Basel, Switzerland, in 1935. After an internship in Istanbul, she came to the Henry Phipps Psychiatric Clinic at Johns Hopkins University to work on insulin therapy for schizophrenia.
Theodore and Ruth Lidz met and married in 1939. Their first son was born in 1941. When, in 1942, Theodore left for military service in the South Pacific with the Johns Hopkins Medical Unit, Ruth was placed in charge of the Phipps chemistry laboratory, became the Hopkins' electroencephalographer, and was psychiatrist to the well-baby clinic. Theodore served in New Zealand, Fiji, and Burma and was the only psychiatrist for several hundred psychiatric casualties from Guadalcanal. On his return to Hopkins in 1946, Theodore became chief of the Psychiatric Section of the Department of Medicine and initiated research on psychosomatic medicine. He continued at Johns Hopkins until 1951, as an instructor and then associate professor. With Ruth, he studied psychiatric problems among parents of patients hospitalized with schizophrenia. This work served as a basis for later studies. While in analysis with Frieda Fromm-Reichmann, Ruth recognized her artistic interests that had been discouraged by her father. In her middle age, she became a fine sculptor in her spare time
In 1951, Ruth and Theodore Lidz moved to New Haven where Theodore was appointed as professor in the Department of Psychiatry at the Yale School of Medicine and psychiatrist-in-chief of the Yale Psychiatric Clinic. Ruth established her psychoanalytic practice and joined the clinical faculty of the Yale Department of Psychiatry in 1965. Theodore was chairman of the department from 1967 to 1969. He was president of the American Psychosomatic Society from 1957 to 1958 and of the American College of Psychoanalysis in 1992. His book, The Person, was widely translated and became a standard text. He received the Frieda Fromm-Reichmann Award of the American Academy of Psychoanalysis, the Stanley Dean Award of the American College of Psychiatrists, the William C. Meninger Award of the American College of Physicians, and the Van Giesen Award of the New York State Psychiatric Institute, primarily for his studies of the relationship between psychiatric disorders and the family environment of the patient. Although he never denied a genetic factor in causing schizophrenia, he disputed the interpretation of the statistical studies of Kety, Wender, and Rosenthal that schizophrenia was primarily a genetic disorder. Both Ruth and Theodore Lidz had reservations about the long term treatment of schizophrenic patients on neuroleptic drugs. The drugs muted negative feelings and outbursts, thus suppressing meaningful material for a therapeutic relationship. They were convinced of the patients' need for psychotherapy
On a trip to the South Pacific in 1970, the Lidzes combined their psychiatric and anthropological interests. Their study of initiation rituals in Papua New Guinea led to their book Oedipus in the Stone Age. They also collected art objects from a variety of cultures. They donated a large collection of their indigenous artifacts to the Peabody Museum of Natural History in 1986.
Although he retired in 1978, Theodore continued to write, lecture, and treat patients into the middle of the 1990s. To the end, he remained eager to convince others about the relevance of the family as an important factor in achieving a more fully integrated psychoanalytic theory. Ruth published twenty-five articles and contributions to books, including Schizophrenia and the Family and The Woman as Patient. Ruth died on October 9, 1995. Theodore died on February 16, 2001. They were survived by three sons, Victor, Charles, and Jerome.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and data files documenting the professional careers of Ruth and Theodore Lidz. The papers focus on their professional lives, particularly from the 1950s to the 1980s, highlighting the Lidzes' study of the importance of the family environment in cases of schizophrenia.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series: I. Ruth Lidz Papers, 1938-1995, n.d. II. General Files, 1939-2000, n.d. III. Writings and Research, 1936-2000, n.d. IV. Teaching, 1947-1972, n.d. V. Personal, 1927-2001, n.d.
Medicine; Psychiatry; Connecticut; Educators; Physicians; Psychiatrists; Lidz, Ruth Wilmanns; Lidz, Theodore; Yale University -- Faculty
- Ruth Lidz Papers, 1938-1995; Series I
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 14 is closed for 75 years from date of creation (2035-2066). Boxes 28-45 are closed for 75 years from date of creation (2011-2060). Researchers may ask to have relevant materials sanitized at their own expense.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes bibliographies, curricula vitae, correspondence, tributes, articles, and lectures of Ruth Lidz, but it reflects only a small portion of her professional activities and nothing of her private practice, teaching, sculpture, or child-rearing efforts. The bulk of the series dates from the 1970s and 1980s. The autobiographical sketches describe her early training and experience. The correspondence here is addressed to Ruth Lidz and is related to her professional work. Additional letters, addressed to both Ruth and Theodore, are included in Series II. Writings are arranged chronologically.
  - Autobiographical sketches, [198-]-[1990?], undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bibliographies, 1988, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Book reviews, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Curricula vitae, 1976, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Data for schizophrenia studies
    General note
    See: Series III, Box 44, Folder 435
  - Personal, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    See also: Series V, Box 48, Folder 1
    See also: Series V, Box 48, Folder 10-11
    See also: Series V, Box 48, Folder 13
  - Tributes and obituaries, 1993, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Writings
    - Women-The World Over [Springfield State Hospital Chips], 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bychowsky's paper [discussion, American Psychoanalytic Association], 1950 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - "An Interpretation of the Perspectives of American Psychiatry", 1950
      See: Series III, Box 20, Folder 30
    - "The Importance of the Woman's Emotional Reactions to the Success of the Pill" [American Psychiatric Association], 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - American Psychoanalytic Association [discussion group on abortion], 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "Why Women Won't Use the Pill" [Mt. Sinai Hospital], 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "The Child at Risk" [discussion, American Psychoanalytic Association], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Contraception [for Human Fertility ], [197-] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Reactions of women before and during contraceptive pill use, [197-] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "Some Comments on the Supervision of the Psychotherapy of Schizophrenic Patients", [197-]
      See: Series III, Box 21, Folder 47
    - "Statement on Abortion", [197-] (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Women and birth control, [197-] (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - "Women's Fertility and Self-Realization", [197-] (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "Yale Guide to Family Assessment" [with S. Fleck et. al.], 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "Positive Aspects of Anger and Anxiety in the Treatment of Schizophrenic Patients" [Germany], 1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Second Annual Cape Cod Summer Symposium, 1987
      See: Series III, Box 25, Folder 180
      See: Series III, Box 25, Folder 181
      See: Series III, Box 25, Folder 182
    - "Sorcery and Societal Integration in Papua New Guinea" [See: 5], 1989
      General
      See: Series III, box 21, folder 52
    - "The Effect of Neurotropic Drugs on the Psychotherapy of Schizophrenic Patients" [Turin], [198-] (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - "Vortrag" [Psychiatrischen Klinik, Heidelberg], 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "The Curative Factors in the Psychotherapy of Schizophrenia", [1994] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - "Anger, Hostility and Anxiety in the Treatment of Schizophrenic Patients", undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Countertransference [outline], undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "Countertransference Problems in the Treatment of Schizophrenic and Borderline Patients", undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - "Emotional Problems in Relation to Fertility Control", undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "Factors Concerning the Recovery of Patients Treated with the Aid of Shock Therapy", undated
      See: Series III, Box 21, Folder 71
    - "Memories of Frieda Fromm-Reichmann", undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "Personality and Emotional Factors in the Success of Contraception" [Yale-New Haven Hospital rounds], undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "'Pill' Conflicts and Symptoms" [Family course, Yale-New Haven Hospital], undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - "Problems of Adolescent Pregnancy", undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - "Psychological Factors in Contraceptive Failure" [Mexico City], undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "Psychological Reactions to the Pill" [abstract], undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Psychotherapy of schizophrenia [Heidelberg], undated
      See: Series III, Box 26, Folder 217
    - Psychotherapy of Schizophrenic Patients- Transference and Countertransference Problems, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Study in the Family Planning Clinic, Yale-New Haven Hospital, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "Transference and Countertransference Problems in the Treatment of Schizophrenic Patients", undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "The Use of Anxiety and Hostility in the Treatment of Schizophrenic Patients", undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
- General files, 1939-2000, undated; Series II
  The series is composed of correspondence, reports, radio programs, and files relating to professional meetings, arranged alphabetically by personal or corporate name. Correspondents include peers, students, organizations, institutions, and publishers. Copies of replies to the letters received are often included. Although the vast majority of letters concern topics in psychiatry, Theodore also wrote to government leaders about political issues, especially human rights abuses. Many of these letters were part of a Freedom Writers program of Amnesty International. The bulk of the material is from 1960s to the 1980s. The series includes correspondence from colleagues who were also friends. Lawrence Kubie probably influenced Theodore's decision to go into psychiatry. Eugene Brody, editor of the Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease, involved Theodore in editorial matters. Frederick Redlich helped recruit Theodore to the Yale Department of Psychiatry, and they continued to work closely together when Redlich became the dean of the Yale Medical School. The series documents Theodore's efforts as a founding fellow and active participant in the American College of Psychoanalysts. The American Journal of Psychiatry files contain references to Theodore's refutation of the Danish-American studies of adopted twins used as subjects to try to prove the genetic component in the etiology of schizophrenia. Gilbert Herdt, anthropologist, and Theodore had common interest in the rituals of New Guinea tribes.
  - A, 1952-1990 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Ackerman, Nathan W., 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Adland, Marvin L., 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Alanen, Yrjo, 1967-1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    See also: Series III, Schizophrenia and the Family studies
  - American College of Physicians, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American College of Psychiatrists, 1971-1997 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - American College of Psychoanalysts
    - General, 1971-1991 (Box 2, Folder 12-20)
    - Colloquium on the Family and Psychoanalytic Theory, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - An American Family [television panel], 1973 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - American Handbook of Psychiatry, 1956-1974 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - American Journal of Psychiatry, 1968-1991 (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
    See also: Series II, Box 11, Folder 266
  - American Mental Health Foundation, 1979-1989 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - American Orthopsychiatric Association, 1954-1988 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - American Psychiatric Association
    - General, 1953-1990 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Committee on Medical Education, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - American Psychoanalytic Association, 1972-1977 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Ammar, Sleim, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Amnesty International [Freedom Writers], 1979-1991 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Anthony, E. James, 1968-1991 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Apter, Nathaniel, 1951-1973 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Arbiter family, 1953-1987 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Aring, Charles D., 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Aronson, Jason, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Association for Research in Nervous and Mental Disease, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Association for the Advancement of Psychoanalysis, 1955-1968 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Astudillo, Alberto, 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - B, 1951-1991 (Box 4, Folder 41-46)
  - Bahnson, Claus B., 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Baker, Grace, 1952-1968 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Balsam, Alan, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Bamdad, Jamil, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Bandler, Bernard, 1968-1990 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Barber, James J., 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Barrera, David, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Basic Books, 1967-1991 (Box 4, Folder 54-61)
  - Batra, Krishan, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Bawer, Theodore, 1968-1974 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Beeson, Paul, 1953-1974 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Bercherie, Paul, 1984-1987 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - Berg, Ivar, 1969-1972 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Berkowitz, David, 1969-1972 (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Berman, Leo H., 1975-1985 (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Bernstein, Lewis, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Blatt, Sidney J., 1969-1989 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Bleuler, Manfred, 1966-1990 (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Bliss, Eugene L., 1952-1989 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Bowers, Malcolm, 1967-1973 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Bowers, Shirley, 1951-1952 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Boyer, L. Bryce, 1967-1989 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Braceland, Francis J., 1953-1975 (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Brewster, Henry H., 1952-1954 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Brody, Eugene B. II, 1951-1990 (Box 5, Folder 78)
    See also: Series II, Box 17, Folder 390
  - Bruch, Hilde, 1952-1974, undated (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Burton, Arthur, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Burton-Bradley, Burton Gyrth, 1971-1989 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - C, 1948-1990 (Box 5, Folder 82-88)
  - Cameron, Norman, 1951-1973 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Cancro, Robert, 1973-1984 (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Carstairs, G. Morris, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Castro de la Mata, Renato, 1967-1990 (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Center for Advanced Study in the Behavioral Sciences, 1967-1989 (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Ciarlo, Dorothy, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 94)
  - Cieri, Alexandra, 1971?-1972 (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Ciompi, Luc, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Cleghorn, Robert A., 1948-1969 (Box 5, Folder 97)
  - Cohen, Robert A., 1954-1970 (Box 5, Folder 98)
  - Columbia University. College of Physicians and Surgeons. Association of Alumni, 1949-1991 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Commonwealth Fund, 1958-1979 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Comprehensive Textbook of Psychiatry, III, 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Conn, Howard F., 1967-1968 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Connecticut. Connecticut Postgraduate Seminar in Psychiatry and Neurology, 1953-1970 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - Connecticut. Governor's Ad Hoc Committee, The Joint Committee of State Mental Hospitals and the Mental Health Committee of the Connecticut State Mental Society, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Connecticut Committee for Soviet Jews, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Connecticut Valley Hospital, 1967-1991 (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Conran, Michael B., 1971-1985 (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Cornelison, Alice R., 1967-1987 (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Coser, Ellen, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Cowgill, Cynthia Wild, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 110)
  - Crank, H. Harlan, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 111)
  - D, 1952-1990 (Box 6, Folder 112-115)
  - Dalgard, Odd, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 116)
  - Dean, Stanley R., 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 117)
  - Delgado, Jose, 1954-1968 (Box 6, Folder 118)
  - Detre, Thomas P., 1967-1969 (Box 6, Folder 119)
  - Dixon, William T., 1968-1975 (Box 6, Folder 120)
  - Dressler, David M., 1972-1974 (Box 6, Folder 121)
  - Duke University Medical Center, 1969-1971 (Box 6, Folder 122)
  - Dulit, Everett, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - E, 1952-1991 (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Ebbert, Arthur, 1968-1975 (Box 6, Folder 125)
  - Elizur, Avner, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 126)
  - Elkins, Robert, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 127)
  - Erskine, Alice, 1956-1989 (Box 6, Folder 128)
  - F, 1952-1991 (Box 6, Folder 129-130)
  - Family Process, 1968-1991 (Box 6, Folder 131)
  - Feinsilver, David, 1967-1989 (Box 6, Folder 132)
  - Fleck, Stephen, 1967-1974 (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - Ford, Gerald R., 1974-1975 (Box 7, Folder 134)
  - Foundations' Fund for Research in Psychiatry, 1966-1971 (Box 7, Folder 135)
  - Freedman, Daniel X., 1966-1970 (Box 7, Folder 136)
  - Freedman, David A., 1973-1984 (Box 7, Folder 137)
  - Friedman, Robert M., 1983-1986 (Box 7, Folder 138)
  - Frosh, John, 1967-1972 (Box 7, Folder 139)
  - Furlan, Pier Maria, 1989-1991 (Box 7, Folder 140)
  - G, 1954-1990 (Box 7, Folder 141-142)
  - Galdstone, Iago, 1970-1973 (Box 7, Folder 143)
  - Galerie Wolfgang Ketterer, 1973-1983 (Box 7, Folder 144)
  - Gallant, Leonard J., 1973-1975 (Box 7, Folder 145)
  - Geigy Pharmaceuticals, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 146)
  - Gill, Merton, 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 147)
  - Ginzberg, Eli, 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 148)
  - Glass, George S., 1971-1973 (Box 7, Folder 149)
  - Glick, Ira D., 1974-1987 (Box 7, Folder 150)
  - Grace New Haven Community Hospital. Psychiatric Outpatient Clinic, 1949-1955 (Box 7, Folder 151)
  - Greenblatt, Milton, 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 152)
  - Guattari, Felix, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 153)
  - Guerrette, Robert S., 1984-1985 (Box 7, Folder 154)
  - Gurman, Alan S., 1985 (Box 7, Folder 155)
  - H, 1969-1991 (Box 7, Folder 156-157)
  - Hafner, Heinz, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 158)
  - Hartmann, Geoffrey, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 159)
  - Harvard University. Visiting Committee, Psychology and Social Relations, 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 160-162)
  - Harvey, A. McGehee, 1974-1989 (Box 8, Folder 163)
  - Hassan, Susana Alicia, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 164)
  - Hawkins, David R., 1970-1989 (Box 8, Folder 165)
  - Hayden, David, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 166)
  - Herdt, Gilbert H., 1979-1989 (Box 8, Folder 167-168)
  - Hirsch, Solomon, 1954-1972 (Box 8, Folder 169)
  - Humanitas, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 170)
  - Hunt, Samuel P., 1972-1976 (Box 8, Folder 171)
  - I, 1969-1989 (Box 8, Folder 172)
  - Integrative Psychiatry, 1981-1983 (Box 8, Folder 173)
  - International Association for Child Psychiatry and Allied Professions, 1969-1970 (Box 8, Folder 174)
  - International Symposium for the Psychotherapy of Schizophrenia
    - Vth II, 1974-1975 (Box 8, Folder 175)
      See also: Series II, Box 8, Folder 187
    - IXth, 1987-1988 (Box 8, Folder 176)
    - Xth, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 177)
  - International Universities Press, 1961-1972 (Box 8, Folder 178)
  - Ithaca Conference on the Teaching of Psychiatry, 1951-1954 (Box 8, Folder 179)
  - J, 1951-1991 (Box 8, Folder 180)
  - Jackson, Don D., 1957-1967 (Box 8, Folder 181)
  - Jacobs, Theodore J., 1969 (Box 8, Folder 182)
  - James, Basil, 1971-1990 (Box 8, Folder 183)
  - Jewish Family and Community Service [Chicago], 1966 (Box 8, Folder 184)
  - Jones, Robert O., 1954-1976 (Box 8, Folder 185)
  - Jones, T. Robert, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 186)
  - Jörstad, Jarl II, 1968-1991 (Box 8, Folder 187)
    See also: Series II, Box 8, Folder 175
  - Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease, 1966-1991 (Box 9, Folder 188-190)
  - Journal of the American Psychoanalytic Association, 1974-1989 (Box 9, Folder 191)
  - K, 1951-1990 (Box 9, Folder 192-195)
  - Katz, Jack L., 1971 (Box 9, Folder 196)
  - Katz, Jay and Pearl, 1967-1986 (Box 9, Folder 197)
  - Kaufman, M. Ralph, 1972-1974 (Box 9, Folder 198)
  - Kaunitz, Paul E., 1954-1968 (Box 9, Folder 199)
  - Keniston, Kenneth, 1967-1975 (Box 9, Folder 200)
  - Kety, Seymour, 1968-1987 (Box 9, Folder 201)
  - Klerman, Gerald, 1967-1985 (Box 9, Folder 202)
  - Klitzman, Robert, 1985-1989 (Box 9, Folder 203)
  - Kohn, Lawrence and Sally, 1951-1984 (Box 9, Folder 204)
  - Kolb, Lawrence C., 1954-1991 (Box 9, Folder 205)
  - Koupernik, Cyrille, 1972-1973 (Box 9, Folder 206)
  - Kraushaar, Meyer, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 207)
  - Kringlen, Einar, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 208)
  - Kubie, Lawrence S., 1950-1973 (Box 9, Folder 209-211)
    See also: Series IV, Box 46, Folder 9
  - L, 1952-1991 (Box 10, Folder 212-216)
  - Laffal, Julius, 1968-1973 (Box 10, Folder 217)
  - Lawton, Robert P., 1967-1968 (Box 10, Folder 218)
  - Lefer, Jay, 1967-1975 (Box 10, Folder 219)
  - Lehrman, Nathaniel S., 1988 (Box 10, Folder 220)
  - Leighton, Alexander, 1951-1975 (Box 10, Folder 221)
  - Lennard, Henry L., 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 222)
  - Levine, Maurice, 1952-1968 (Box 10, Folder 223)
  - Lewis, Bernard I., 1952-1954 (Box 10, Folder 224)
  - Lichter, Jesse and Barbara, 1970-1976 (Box 10, Folder 225)
  - Lidz family, 1952-2000 (Box 10, Folder 226)
  - Literature and Psychology, 1964-1965 (Box 10, Folder 227)
  - Loewald, Hans W., 1953-1975 (Box 10, Folder 228)
  - Lowenbach, Hans, 1953 (Box 10, Folder 229)
  - Lustman, Seymour L., 1967-1969 (Box 10, Folder 230)
  - M, 1939-1991 (Box 10, Folder 231-236)
  - Marx, Otto, 1990-1991 (Box 11, Folder 237)
  - Maryland Psychiatric Society, 1949-2000 (Box 11, Folder 238)
    See also: Series III, Box 20, Folder 29